<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<LanguageData>
  
  <!-- EN: baseliner -->
  <Baseliner.label>básico</Baseliner.label>
  <!-- EN: A naturally-evolved human with no major significant genetic modifications. -->
  <Baseliner.description>Un humano que ha evolucionado de forma natural sin grandes modificaciones genéticas.</Baseliner.description>
  
  <!-- EN: dirtmole -->
  <Dirtmole.label>terra-topo</Dirtmole.label>
  <!-- EN: With gray skin adapted to artificial light, they thrive in cramped and dark spaces where combat and travel happen over short distances. They are extremely capable at digging or mining tasks. In the open, however, they suffer from a sensitivity to light, slow speed and poor eyesight at distance.\n\nAfter the first tunnel colonies failed due to the stress of confinement, colonization agencies began genetically altering colonists to live without open space or sunlight. This xenotype is known colloquially as the dirtmoles. Today, dirtmoles have expanded out of their original tunnel homes and rule many confined spaces in the anthrosphere. They can be found in deep mines, cramped low-tech spacecraft, and teeming by the billions in the dark underlayers of countless urbworlds. -->
  <Dirtmole.description>Con una piel gris adaptada a la luz artificial, prosperan en espacios estrechos y oscuros donde el combate y los desplazamientos se producen en distancias cortas. Son extremadamente capaces en tareas de excavación o minería. Sin embargo, en campo abierto, sufren de sensibilidad a la luz, lentitud y mala visión a distancia.\n\nDespués de que las primeras colonias de túneles fracasaran debido al estrés del confinamiento, las agencias de colonización comenzaron a alterar genéticamente a los colonos para que vivieran sin espacio abierto ni luz solar. Este xenotipo se conoce coloquialmente como topos de tierra. Hoy en día, los terra-topos se han expandido fuera de sus hogares originales en los túneles y dominan muchos espacios confinados en la antrosfera. Se les puede encontrar en minas profundas, en naves espaciales de baja tecnología y pululando por miles de millones en los oscuros subsuelos de innumerables mundos urbe.</Dirtmole.description>
  <!-- EN: With gray skin adapted to artificial light, dirtmoles thrive in cramped and dark spaces where combat and travel happen over short distances. They are naturals at digging and navigating complex tunnel structures. In the open, they suffer from a sensitivity to light, slow speed and poor eyesight at distance. -->
  <Dirtmole.descriptionShort>Con una piel gris adaptada a la luz artificial, los terra-topos prosperan en espacios estrechos y oscuros donde el combate y los viajes se producen en distancias cortas. Son expertos en la excavación y en la construcción de túneles complejos. En campo abierto, sufren de sensibilidad a la luz, lentitud y mala visión a distancia.</Dirtmole.descriptionShort>
  
  <!-- EN: genie -->
  <Genie.label>genio</Genie.label>
  <!-- EN: Designed to be engineers, genies' delicate bones and natural aptitude with machines allow them to manipulate devices with remarkable precision. They are emotionally cold and can follow orders where others might panic. However, they are fragile, and their amplified nerve impulses make them easy to debilitate with relatively little pain. With so much of their brains dedicated to analyzing machines, they lack the neural hardware to analyze emotions, so they sometimes come off as socially inept. Their dead calm makes it even harder for them to relate to what they see as madly-hotheaded baseliner humans.\n\nGenies were engineered thousands of years ago by a long-disbanded space navy to hold engineering positions on large starships. Today, genies still serve as engineers in great cities and fleets, but many can also be found working as lawyers, pilots, and musicians. -->
  <Genie.description>Diseñados para ser ingenieros, los delicados huesos de los genios y su aptitud natural con las máquinas les permiten manipular dispositivos con notable precisión. Son emocionalmente fríos y pueden seguir órdenes donde otros podrían entrar en pánico. Sin embargo, son frágiles y sus impulsos nerviosos amplificados los hacen fáciles de debilitar con relativamente poco dolor. Al dedicar gran parte de su cerebro al análisis de las máquinas, carecen del hardware neural para analizar las emociones, por lo que a veces resultan socialmente ineptos. Su calma absoluta hace que sea aún más difícil para ellos relacionarse con lo que ven como humanos básicos locamente exaltados.\n\nLos genios fueron creados hace miles de años por una armada espacial disuelta hace tiempo para ocupar puestos de ingeniería en grandes naves estelares. Hoy en día, los genios siguen trabajando como ingenieros en grandes ciudades y flotas, pero muchos también pueden trabajar como abogados, pilotos y músicos.</Genie.description>
  <!-- EN: Designed to be engineers, genies have natural aptitude with machines, and are emotionally cold and calm. They are also fragile and vulnerable to pain. Focused on machines, they often come off as socially inept. -->
  <Genie.descriptionShort>Diseñados para ser ingenieros, los genios tienen aptitudes naturales con las máquinas y son emocionalmente fríos y tranquilos. También son frágiles y vulnerables al dolor. Centrados en las máquinas, suelen ser socialmente ineptos.</Genie.descriptionShort>
  
  <!-- EN: highmate -->
  <Highmate.label>súcubo</Highmate.label>
  <!-- EN: Designed companions and concubines with a unique ability to psychically bond with a mate, highmates are empathic, beautiful, cheerful, and talented in social matters. They are also inept at manual tasks, physically weak, and mentally incapable of violence.\n\nOn a few wealthy worlds, highmate xenogerms are commercially available and some people become highmates as a sort of career. However, many societies find them abhorrent, either because they distract people from forming natural families, or because they are humans shaped to serve the pleasures of another. On such worlds they are either reserved as playthings of the powerful, or banned entirely. This particular line of highmate fits the fashions of classical Novaroma, but many other variants exist. -->
  <Highmate.description>Diseñados como compañeros y concubinos con una capacidad única para vincularse psíquicamente con un compañero, los súcubos son empáticos, bellos, alegres y con talento para las cuestiones sociales. También son ineptos para las tareas manuales, físicamente débiles y mentalmente incapaces de ejercer la violencia.\n\nEn unos pocos mundos ricos, los xenogérmenes de los súcubos están disponibles comercialmente y algunas personas se convierten en súcubos como una especie de carrera profesional. Sin embargo, muchas sociedades los consideran aborrecibles, bien porque distraen a la gente de la formación de familias naturales, o bien porque son humanos moldeados para servir a los placeres de otro. En estos mundos se reservan como juguetes de los poderosos o se prohíben por completo. Esta línea particular de súcubos se ajusta a las modas de la Novaroma clásica, pero existen muchas otras variantes.</Highmate.description>
  <!-- EN: Designed companions and concubines with a unique ability to psychically bond with a mate, highmates are empathic, beautiful, cheerful, and talented in social matters. They are also inept at manual tasks, physically weak, and mentally incapable of violence. -->
  <Highmate.descriptionShort>Diseñados como compañeros y concubinos con una capacidad única para vincularse psíquicamente con un compañero, los súcubos son empáticos, bellos, alegres y con talento para las cuestiones sociales. También son ineptos para las tareas manuales, físicamente débiles y mentalmente incapaces de ejercer la violencia.</Highmate.descriptionShort>
  
  <!-- EN: hussar -->
  <Hussar.label>húsar</Hussar.label>
  <!-- EN: Hussars are engineered soldiers. They fight aggressively and with precision, heal fast, thrive in extreme temperatures, and freely ingest military drugs. They have a genetic dependence on go-juice, which also makes them less likely to rebel against their commanders.\n\nWhile hussars' emotions make them dangerous in combat, they can't relate to baseliner humans. They are famous for their blood-red eyes and "hussar stare", a dead expression that unsettles many people. Their lack of expression and burning aggressive nature has led to many violent misunderstandings.\n\nIn most societies where they live, hussars are kept separated from the rest of the population. Hussars are single-purpose tools - and they generally aren't bothered by the fact. -->
  <Hussar.description>Los húsar son soldados diseñados por ingenieros. Luchan con agresividad y precisión, se curan rápidamente, prosperan en temperaturas extremas e ingieren libremente drogas militares. Tienen una dependencia genética del neurozumo, lo que les hace menos propensos a rebelarse contra sus comandantes.\n\nAunque las emociones de los húsar los hacen peligrosos en combate, no pueden relacionarse con los humanos básicos. Son famosos por sus ojos rojos como la sangre y su "mirada de húsar", una expresión muerta que inquieta para mucha gente. Su falta de expresión y su ardiente naturaleza agresiva han provocado muchos malentendidos violentos.\n\nEn la mayoría de las sociedades en las que viven, los húsar se mantienen separados del resto de la población. Los húsar son herramientas de un solo uso, y generalmente no les molesta este hecho.</Hussar.description>
  <!-- EN: Hussars are engineered soldiers. They fight aggressively and with precision, heal fast, thrive in extreme temperatures, and freely ingest military drugs. They have a genetic dependence on go-juice. -->
  <Hussar.descriptionShort>Los húsares son soldados diseñados por ingenieros. Luchan con agresividad y precisión, se curan rápidamente, prosperan en temperaturas extremas e ingieren libremente drogas militares. Tienen una dependencia genética del neurozumo.</Hussar.descriptionShort>
  
  <!-- EN: impid -->
  <Impid.label>diablillo</Impid.label>
  <!-- EN: Made for desert life, impid cultures live on many rimworlds and dry deathworlds. Impids are extremely fast-moving, easily tolerate high temperatures, and can spew fire from their mouths. Though they are masters on the sand, impids struggle in other environments. They are terrible with farming. They fight well at range, but in close combat their physical weakness becomes apparent.\n\nOutlanders call them dustrunners because of their speed over open terrain and resistance to heat. Some tribes call them devils because of their horns and because they burn their enemies. Impid tribes' combat tactics usually center on rapid-approach incendiary attacks using both handheld fire weapons and their fire spew ability. -->
  <Impid.description>Hechos para la vida en el desierto, las culturas de diablillo viven en muchos mundos fronterizos y mundos muertos. Los diablillos son extremadamente rápidos, toleran fácilmente las altas temperaturas y pueden escupir fuego por la boca. Aunque son maestros en la arena, los diablillos tienen dificultades en otros entornos. Son terribles con la agricultura. Luchan bien a distancia, pero en el combate cuerpo a cuerpo su debilidad física se hace presente.\n\nLos forasteros los llaman corredores de polvo por su velocidad en campo abierto y su resistencia al calor. Algunas tribus los llaman demonios por sus cuernos y porque queman a sus enemigos. Las tácticas de combate de las tribus impías suelen centrarse en ataques incendiarios de aproximación rápida utilizando tanto armas de fuego de mano como su habilidad de escupir fuego.</Impid.description>
  <!-- EN: Made for desert life, impids are very fast, can spew fire from their mouths, and easily tolerate high temperatures. They fight well at range, but in close combat they do little damage. They are terrible with farming, and have weak immune systems. -->
  <Impid.descriptionShort>Hechos para la vida en el desierto, los diablillos son muy rápidos, pueden escupir fuego por la boca y toleran fácilmente las altas temperaturas. Luchan bien a distancia, pero en el combate cuerpo a cuerpo hacen poco daño. Son terribles con la agricultura y tienen un sistema inmunológico débil.</Impid.descriptionShort>
  
  <!-- EN: neanderthal -->
  <Neanderthal.label>neandertal</Neanderthal.label>
  <!-- EN: Neanderthals are stocky, powerfully-built humanoids. Their most salient characteristic is that they are difficult to hurt: They are very resistant to injury, and their strong immune systems protect them from infection. However, without ever having evolved in a complex civilization, they are less adept than baseliner humans at intellectual and social tasks, and their impulsiveness can make them dangerously aggressive.\n\nHomo neanderthalensis was originally an archaic population of hominids that emerged over 200,000 years ago during the Pleistocene epoch. After they were replaced by and merged with humans 30,000 years ago, they were absent for tens of thousands of years until scientists resurrected them from ancient DNA. Neanderthals now survive in sub-societies on some settled planets. On the rimworlds, neanderthal tribes carve out the same existence as their Earth ancestors did so long ago. -->
  <Neanderthal.description>Los neandertales son humanoides fornidos y de complexión fuerte. Su característica más notable es que son difíciles de herir: Son muy resistentes a las lesiones y su fuerte sistema inmunitario les protege de las infecciones. Sin embargo, al no haber evolucionado nunca hacia una civilización compleja, son menos hábiles que los humanos básicos en tareas intelectuales y sociales, y su impulsividad puede hacerlos peligrosamente agresivos.\n\nEl Homo neanderthalensis era originalmente una población arcaica de homínidos que surgió hace más de 200.000 años durante el Pleistoceno. Tras ser sustituidos por los humanos y fusionarse con ellos hace 30.000 años, estuvieron ausentes durante decenas de miles de años hasta que los científicos los resucitaron a partir de ADN antiguo. En la actualidad, los neandertales sobreviven en subsociedades en algunos planetas asentados. En los mundos fronterizos, las tribus neandertales se ganan la vida como lo hicieron sus antepasados terrestres hace tanto tiempo.</Neanderthal.description>
  <!-- EN: Neanderthals are stocky, powerfully-built humanoids. They are hardy and difficult to injure, and their strong immune systems protect them from infection. However, their minds are less adept at intellectual and social tasks, and their impulsiveness can make them dangerously aggressive. -->
  <Neanderthal.descriptionShort>Los neandertales son humanoides fornidos y de complexión fuerte. Son resistentes y difíciles de herir, y su fuerte sistema inmunológico les protege de las infecciones. Sin embargo, sus mentes son menos hábiles en tareas intelectuales y sociales, y su impulsividad puede hacerlos peligrosamente agresivos.</Neanderthal.descriptionShort>
  
  <!-- EN: pigskin -->
  <Pigskin.label>pielcerdo</Pigskin.label>
  <!-- EN: Pigskins are human-pig hybrids which are capable of two-legged movement, tool use, and speech, but which also retain many pig-like qualities. They are hardy and can eat almost anything without getting sick, but their trotter-shaped hands leave them at a disadvantage when attempting to precisely manipulate tools and objects. They don't see well at a distance, so pigskin gangs usually focus on close-range weapons. They also have a strong taste for explosives.\n\nPigskins were made for their organs. Uncomfortable with the idea of harvesting organs from baseliner humans, a long-gone government merged human DNA into pigs to make the animals produce more easily-transplantable hearts and lungs. They succeeded, but the resulting creatures became more humanlike than anyone anticipated. -->
  <Pigskin.description>Los pielescerdo son híbridos humano-cerdos capaces de moverse a dos patas, utilizar herramientas y hablar, pero que también conservan muchas cualidades de los cerdos. Son resistentes y pueden comer casi cualquier cosa sin enfermar, pero sus manos con forma de pezuñas les dejan en desventaja cuando intentan manipular con precisión herramientas y objetos. No ven bien a distancia, por lo que las bandas de cerdos suelen centrarse en las armas de corto alcance. También tienen un gran gusto por los explosivos.\n\nLos pielescerdo fueron creados por sus órganos. Incómodos con la idea de extraer órganos de seres humanos básicos, un antiguo gobierno fusionó ADN humano en cerdos para que los animales produjeran corazones y pulmones más fáciles de trasplantar. Lo consiguieron, pero las criaturas resultantes se asemejaron más a los humanos de lo que nadie esperaba.</Pigskin.description>
  <!-- EN: Pigskins are human-pig hybrids. They are hardy and can eat almost anything without getting sick, but their trotter-shaped hands are bad at fine manipulation. They don't see well at a distance, so they usually focus on close-range weapons. They have a strong taste for explosives. -->
  <Pigskin.descriptionShort>Los pielescerdo son híbridos de humano y cerdo. Son resistentes y pueden comer casi cualquier cosa sin enfermar, pero sus manos con forma de pezuñas son malas para la manipulación fina. No ven bien a distancia, por lo que suelen centrarse en las armas de corto alcance. Tienen un gran gusto por los explosivos.</Pigskin.descriptionShort>
  
  <!-- EN: sanguophage -->
  <Sanguophage.label>sanguífago</Sanguophage.label>
  <!-- EN: Sanguophages are a type of archotech-enhanced xenohuman. Powered by archites, their abilities go far beyond normal genetic enhancements. They are mentally adept and preternaturally beautiful. In combat, they can launch deadly spines and heal injured friends. They don't age or die naturally and never suffer from disease or poison. A sanguophage can make a new sanguophage by reimplanting their own xenogerm into a person.\n\nSanguophages must regularly consume hemogen derived from human blood, and they must periodically deathrest for long periods. They're easily destroyed by fire, and slowed down by UV light.\n\nThe first sanguophage appeared thousands of years ago when the lord-explorer Varan-Dur sought to control a hyperintelligent archotech and found himself transformed by it instead. Every sanguophage is descended from him. Since then, sanguophages have often been hunted because of their destabilizing power and their need for blood. Since they can pass for baseliners, many live in hiding among typical humans.\n\nTheir numbers are unknown. Some think they are legends or rare irrelevancies. Some believe sanguophages secretly direct entire human civilizations. The stories speak of eternal lords ruling billions from slate-black space stations, or directing blood sacrifices at conferences in the underlayers of the deepest urbworlds. -->
  <Sanguophage.description>Los sanguífagos son un tipo de xenohumanos mejorados arqueotecnológicamente. Impulsados por las arquitas, sus habilidades van mucho más allá de las mejoras genéticas normales. Son mentalmente hábiles y de una belleza sobrenatural. En combate, pueden lanzar espinas mortales y curar a sus amigos heridos. No envejecen ni mueren de forma natural y nunca sufren enfermedades ni venenos. Un sanguífago puede crear un nuevo sanguífago reimplantando su propio xenogermen en una persona.\n\nLos sanguífagos deben consumir regularmente hemógeno derivado de la sangre humana y deben mortisoñar regularmente durante largos periodos. Son fácilmente destruidos por el fuego, y ralentizados por la luz ultravioleta.\n\nEl primer sanguífago apareció hace miles de años, cuando el señor-explorador Varan-Dur intentó controlar una hiperinteligencia arqueoteca y se encontró transformado por esta. Todos los sanguífagos descienden de él. Desde entonces, los sanguífagos han sido perseguidos a menudo por su poder desestabilizador y su necesidad de sangre. Como pueden pasar por básicos, muchos viven escondidos entre los humanos típicos.\n\nSu número es desconocido. Algunos creen que son leyendas o raras irrelevancias. Algunos creen que los sanguífagos dirigen en secreto civilizaciones humanas enteras. Las historias hablan de señores eternos que gobiernan a miles de millones de personas desde estaciones espaciales de color negro pizarra, o que dirigen sacrificios de sangre en conferencias en el subsuelo de los mundos urbanos más profundos.</Sanguophage.description>
  <!-- EN: Sanguophages are ageless, deathless super-humans powered by archotech-created archites in the bloodstream. They are beautiful and extremely intelligent. They can heal any injury, and never suffer from disease or poison. In combat, they can launch deadly spines and heal injured friends. The price is that sanguophages must consume hemogen derived from human blood to survive, and they must periodically deathrest for long periods. They're easily destroyed by fire, and slowed down by UV light. -->
  <Sanguophage.descriptionShort>Los sanguífago son superhumanos eternos e inmortales, impulsados por arquitas creadas por la arqueotecnólogia en el torrente sanguíneo. Son hermosos y extremadamente inteligentes. Pueden curar cualquier herida y nunca sufren enfermedades ni venenos. En combate, pueden lanzar espinas mortales y curar a sus amigos heridos. El precio es que los sanguífagos deben consumir el hemógeno derivado de la sangre humana para sobrevivir, y deben mortisoñar regularmente durante largos periodos. Son fácilmente destruidos por el fuego y ralentizados por la luz ultravioleta.</Sanguophage.descriptionShort>
  
  <!-- EN: waster -->
  <Waster.label>escoria</Waster.label>
  <!-- EN: Wasters are aggressive, immune to toxic pollution, almost impervious to disease, and can ingest as much psychite and wake-up drugs as they wish with no ill effects. Their toxin-adapted metabolism means they must consume some form of psychite - usually flake or yayo.\n\nOriginally engineered to prevent resettlement of post-apocalyptic deathworlds, wasters are living area-denial weapons. Waster pirates armed with toxic weapons are the bane of many frontier peoples, both on the rimworlds and in the depths of the urbworld hyperstructures. -->
  <Waster.description>Los escorias son agresivos, inmunes a la contaminación tóxica, casi insensibles a las enfermedades, y pueden ingerir tanta psiquita y drogas de despertar como deseen sin ningún efecto negativo. Su metabolismo adaptado a las toxinas significa que deben consumir alguna forma de psiquita, normalmente escamas o yayo.\n\nDiseñados originalmente para evitar el reasentamiento de los mundos muertos postapocalípticos, los escorias son armas vivas de negación de área. Los piratas escoria, armados con armas tóxicas, son la perdición de muchos pueblos fronterizos, tanto en los mundos fronterizos como en las profundidades de las hiperestructuras de los mundos urbe.</Waster.description>
  <!-- EN: Wasters are aggressive, immune to toxic pollution, almost impervious to disease, and can ingest as much psychite and wake-up drugs as they wish with no ill effects. Their toxin-adapted metabolism means they must consume some form of psychite - usually flake or yayo. -->
  <Waster.descriptionShort>Los escorias son agresivos, inmunes a la contaminación tóxica, casi insensibles a las enfermedades, y pueden ingerir tanta psiquita y drogas de despertar como deseen sin ningún efecto negativo. Su metabolismo adaptado a las toxinas significa que deben consumir alguna forma de psiquita, normalmente escamas o yayo.</Waster.descriptionShort>
  
  <!-- EN: yttakin -->
  <Yttakin.label>yttakin</Yttakin.label>
  <!-- EN: Yttakin descend from colonists engineered to thrive on ultra-cold planets. Their great size and fur make them hardy in frozen environments. Yttakin share a psychic connection with the wildlife and can summon animals to their side during battles. They are not fast or energetic or precise, but can keep going when others would have collapsed long before.\n\nSince they migrated off their icy birthworld of Yttak, Yttakin settlements live on many planets. Their fur, roaring voices, and aversion to urban living sometimes leads naive outsiders to believe they are simple-minded animals. Quick-minded Yttakin are happy to make good use of such wrong beliefs, whether at the negotiating table or on the battlefield. -->
  <Yttakin.description>Los Yttakin descienden de colonos diseñados para prosperar en planetas ultrafríos. Su gran tamaño y su pelaje los hacen resistentes en entornos helados. Los Yttakin comparten una conexión psíquica con la fauna y pueden convocar a los animales a su lado durante las batallas. No son rápidos ni enérgicos ni precisos, pero pueden seguir adelante cuando otros se habrían derrumbado mucho antes.\n\nDesde que emigraron de su gélido mundo natal, Yttak, los asentamientos de Yttakin viven en muchos planetas. Su pelaje, sus voces rugientes y su aversión a la vida urbana hacen que los ingenuos forasteros crean a veces que son animales de mente simple. Los Yttakin, de mente rápida, están encantados de hacer buen uso de esas creencias erróneas, ya sea en la mesa de negociaciones o en el campo de batalla.</Yttakin.description>
  <!-- EN: Yttakin descend from colonists engineered to thrive on ultra-cold planets. Their great size and fur make them hardy in frozen environments, and they have a unique ability to communicate vocally and psychically with animals. They are not fast or energetic or precise, but can keep going when others would have collapsed long before. -->
  <Yttakin.descriptionShort>Los Yttakin descienden de colonos diseñados para prosperar en planetas ultrafríos. Su gran tamaño y su pelaje los hacen resistentes en entornos helados, y tienen una capacidad única para comunicarse vocal y psíquicamente con los animales. No son rápidos ni enérgicos ni precisos, pero pueden seguir adelante cuando otros se habrían derrumbado mucho antes.</Yttakin.descriptionShort>
  
</LanguageData>