<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<LanguageData>
  
  <!-- EN: Anomaly -->
  <Anomaly.label>Anomaly</Anomaly.label>
  <!-- EN: Awaken the monolith and provoke the insane machine-mind. Anomaly is a horror-themed expansion that adds diverse and twisted threats and lets you build containment facilities for dark entities.\n\nTrack down an invisible hunter that steals people's souls. Test and interrogate your people to find out who is infested with a mind-controlling parasite. Destroy a fleshmass infestation before it grows over the whole map and consumes everything. Tamper with obelisks that duplicate, mutate, and abduct your colonists. Venture into underground caverns and kill the momma beast below.\n\nBuild a grand containment facility for capturing and studying monsters. Use the power of captured creatures against your enemies. Harvest them for resources to craft void-powered weapons, equipment, apparel, and serums.\n\nFight macabre cultists to stop them from kidnapping your people with their psychic rituals. Use those same rituals for your own purposes and summon the massed dead, rain rage-filled blood, or steal the minds and health of your foes.\n\nChoose your fate in the new endgame as an abyssal void swallows the world.\n\nThis expansion includes a new album of music by Alistair Lindsay. -->
  <Anomaly.description>Despierta al monolito y provoca a la demencial mente de la máquina. Anomaly es una expansión de temática de terror que añade diversas y retorcidas amenazas que te permitirán construir instalaciones de confinamiento para entidades oscuras.\n\nExamina e interroga a tu gente para descubrir quién está infectado con un parásito que controla la mente. Destruye una infestación de masas de carne antes de que crezca por todo el mapa y lo consuma todo. Manipula obeliscos que duplican, mutan y secuestran a tus colonos. Aventúrate en las cavernas subterráneas y mata a la bestia madre. Construye una gran instalación de contención para capturar y estudiar monstruos. Usa el poder de las criaturas capturadas contra tus enemigos. Obtén recursos para fabricar armas, equipamiento, ropa y sueros potenciados por el vacío.\n\nLucha contra siniestros cultistas para impedir que secuestren a tus colonos con sus rituales psíquicos. Usa esos mismos rituales para tus propios fines e invoca a los muertos en masa, haz llover sangre cargada de ira o acaba con la salud física y mental de tus enemigos.\n\nElige tu destino en el nuevo final mientras un vacío abisal se traga el mundo.\n\nEsta expansión incluye un nuevo álbum de música de Alistair Lindsay.</Anomaly.description>
  
  <!-- EN: Biotech -->
  <Biotech.label>Biotech</Biotech.label>
  <!-- EN: Raise a family, control mechanoids, and genetically-modify humans.\n\nBuild nurseries, play with babies, keep them happy and fed. Babies grow up into children who play, get into trouble, learn, and take lessons. Give the kids a rich childhood, or leave them in a growth vat until they're adults. \n\nBuild and control new kinds of mechanoids. Create combat and labor mechanoids and grow your swarm to a fearsome army and workforce. \n\nManage the pollution produced by your mechanoids. Freeze it, export it, destroy it with high-tech atomizers, or adapt to it.\n\nCall down three new hyper-deadly commander mechanoids and defeat them for their ancient technology.\n\nGenetically-modify your colonists or prisoners. Curate a collection of genes through trade, quest rewards, and surgical extractions. Recombine and implant genes to customize people to their purpose.\n\nInteract with new factions of brutish pig-people, toxin-immune human bioweapons, fur-covered animal-controlling arctic settlers, fire-breathing horned desert imps, psychic-bonding super-mates, and more.\n\nExplore the dark power of the secret blood-drinkers and use it to live forever. -->
  <Biotech.description>Forma una familia, controla mecanoides y modifica humanos genéticamente.\n\nConstruye guarderías, juega con los bebés y mantenlos alimentados y felices. Los bebés crecen hasta ser niños que juegan, se meten en problemas, aprenden y reciben clases. Dale a los niños una buena infancia, o déjalos en una incubadora hasta que sean adultos. \n\nConstruye y controla nuevos tipos de mecanoides. Crea mecanoides de trabajo y combate y forma tu ejército de guerreros y trabajadores. \n\nGestiona la contaminación que provocan tus mecanoides. Congela los desechos, expórtalos o destrúyelos con atomizadores, o adáptate a ellos.\n\nInvoca tres nuevos y letales comandantes mecanoides, y derrótalos para obtener su tecnología.\n\nModifica genéticamente a tus colonos o prisioneros. Forma una colección de genes mediante el comercio, misiones o extracciones quirúrjicas. Recombina e implanta genes para personalizar a la gente para un propósito.\n\nInteractúa con nuevas facciones de gente-cerdo agresiva, armas biológicas humanas inmunes, colonos árticos de piel peluda controladores de animales, diablillos del desierto con cuernos que escupen fuego, supercompañeros psíquicos y mucho más.\n\nExplora el poder oscuro de los chupasangres secretos y úsalo para vivir eternamente.</Biotech.description>
  
  <!-- EN: Core -->
  <Core.label>Core</Core.label>
  <!-- EN: Core RimWorld content. -->
  <Core.description>El contenido base de RimWorld.</Core.description>
  
  <!-- EN: Ideology -->
  <Ideology.label>Ideology</Ideology.label>
  <!-- EN: Create your own belief system with fine control over behaviors, preferences, rituals, symbols, and more. Play as pirate nudist cannibals, blind undergrounder mole people, charitable ranching cowboys, machine-obsessed transhumanists, and more.\n\nAssign social roles like leader, moral guide, and specialist to your colonists.\n\nHold unforgettable rituals: Dance parties, cannibal feasts, burn and smoke circles, skylantern festivals, sacrifices, gladiator duels, blindings, scarifications, funerals, and more.\n\nConnect with Gauranlen trees and command the dryads that live inside them.\n\nHunt for ancient relics. Explore long-forgotten ruins, hack downed spacedrones, and infiltrate tribal villages. Attract wealthy pilgrims by presenting your relics in reliquaries. Plunder ancient complexes for treasure. Raid temporary encampments. Help beggars in need, or betray them.\n\nEnslave prisoners to perform work or fight for you.\n\nPlace many new buildings linked to belief systems, and see the many visual styles of different beliefs.\n\nUse new apparel, tattoos, and hairstyles desired by believers.\n\nSeek transcendence through a machine god in the new archonexus endgame. -->
  <Ideology.description>Crea tu propio sistema de creencias con un fino control sobre comportamientos, preferencias, rituales, símbolos y mucho más. Juega como piratas nudistas caníbales, gente ciega subterránea, vaqueros caritativos, transhumanistas obsesionados con las máquinas, y mucho más.\n\nAsigna roles sociales como líder, guía moral y especialista a tus colonos.\n\nRealiza rituales inolvidables: fiestas de baile, festines caníbales, círculos de fuego y humo, festivales de linternas, sacrificios, duelos de gladiadores, cegueras, laceraciones, funerales y mucho más.\n\nConecta con árboles Gauranlen y da órdenes a las dríadas de su interior.\n\nVe a la caza de reliquias ancestrales.\n\nExplora ruinas olvidadas, hackea drones espaciales derribados e infíltrate en aldeas tribales. Atrae a ricos peregrinos presentando tus reliquias en relicarios. Saquea complejos antiguos en busca de tesoros. Asalta campamentos temporales. Ayuda a los mendigos que lo necesiten o traiciónalos.\n\nEsclaviza a los prisioneros para que realicen trabajos o luchen para ti.\n\nConstruye muchos edificios nuevos relacionados con los sistemas de creencias, y observa los muchos estilos visuales de las diferentes creencias.\n\nUsa la nueva ropa, los tatuajes y los peinados deseados por los creyentes.\n\nBusca la trascendencia a través de un dios máquina en el nuevo final del arqueonexo.</Ideology.description>
  
  <!-- EN: Odyssey -->
  <Odyssey.label>Odyssey</Odyssey.label>
  <!-- EN: Build your own ship and travel across the planet!\n\nStart small: just a grav engine, a few rooms, thrusters, and enough fuel to lift off. Over time, make it into a home by adding living quarters, labs, workshops, and everything else your mobile colony needs.\n\nExplore new biomes like the fungal glowforests, glacial plains, and toxic scarlands. Search through crashlanded orbital platforms, insect-infested caves, and other dangerous locations for ancient tech to upgrade your ship.\n\nFly into space. Land on collapsed space stations, ore-rich asteroids, and derelict satellites. Search for treasure, but be prepared for a fight with other orbital scavengers and mechanoid defenses.\n\nTame, train, and trade cute new animals that can fly and swim. Teach them to dig and forage, nuzzle your colonists, and track down your foes.\n\nFollow maps and rumours to find quests across the planet. Hunt the alpha thrumbo, raid ancient cryptosleep bunkers, mine through asteroids to loot stashes, and more.\n\nFace the mechhive in a new end game. Seize control of the machine mind, or destroy it for good.\n\nListen to a new album of music by Alistair Lindsay. -->
  <Odyssey.description>¡Construye tu propia nave y recorre el planeta!\n\nEmpieza con algo sencillo: un solo motor gravitacional, unas cuantas habitaciones, propulsores y suficiente combustible para despegar. Con el tiempo, conviértela en un hogar añadiendo dormitorios, laboratorios, talleres y todo lo que tu colonia móvil necesite.\n\nExplora nuevos biomas, como los lumibosques fúngicos, las llanuras glaciales y las tóxicas tierras escarificadas. Recorre plataformas orbitales estrelladas, cuevas infestadas de insectoides y otros lugares peligrosos en busca de tecnología antigua para mejorar tu nave.\n\nVuela al espacio. Aterriza en estaciones espaciales colapsadas, asteroides ricos en minerales y satélites abandonados. Busca tesoros, pero prepárate para enfrentarte a otros saqueadores orbitales y a las defensas de los mecanoides.\n\nDomestica, entrena y comercia con adorables nuevos animales que pueden volar y nadar. Enséñales a excavar, forrajear, acariciar a tus colonos y rastrear a tus enemigos.\n\nSigue mapas y rumores para encontrar misiones por todo el planeta. Caza al trumbo alfa, asalta búnkeres del criptosueño, excava en asteroides para saquear escondites… ¡y mucho más!\n\nEnfréntate a la mecacolmena en un nuevo final del juego. Toma el control de la mente máquina o destrúyela para siempre.\n\nEscucha y disfruta un nuevo álbum musical compuesto por Alistair Lindsay.</Odyssey.description>
  
  <!-- EN: Royalty -->
  <Royalty.label>Royalty</Royalty.label>
  <!-- EN: Fight or ally with the new Shattered Empire faction.\n\nGain psychic powers through noble right, tribal nature communion, or artifact theft. Strengthen them through meditation, and use them to win battles and socially influence people. Strengthen your psychic power by meditating in grand thronerooms, in nature, before flames, the dead or blank walls.\n\nComplete quests to earn honor and titles, or riches and gear. Host rich nobles, poor refugees, animals, prisoners, and more. Defend crashed shuttles, serve as aerial shock troops, build monuments, defeat enemies, and recruit visitors.\n\nUse the special privileges of nobility to call Imperial troops, shuttles, and orbital strikes.\n\nNew mechanoid clusters may deploy on your map. Wear them down with artillery, do sneaky sabotage, or lure enemies into the danger.\n\nWield persona weapons with unique traits. Use jump packs for tactical flight and shield packs for emergency defense. Wear cataphract armor, locust armor, grenadier armor, and phoenix armor, each with different tools. Install new body implants to augment brains, stomachs, arms, and skin.\n\nEnjoy a new album of music by Alistair Lindsay.\n\nHost and protect the Stellarch and his guards complete the new royal endgame quest. -->
  <Royalty.description>El Imperio ha llegado. Su honrada cultura posee tecnología hiper-avanzada, mientras siguen respetando sus antiguas tradiciones de reyes, reinas, títulos y honor.\n\nObtén títulos reales. Construye fastuosos salones del trono y cámaras reales. Llama a las tropas de élite Imperiales y utiliza las exclusivas armas vinculadas del Imperio.\n\nHaz uso de nuevas habilidades psíquicas. Ciega, controla mentalmente, e induce náuseas y locura. Otros poderes incluyen teletransporte, negar el dolor, o volverse invisible, entre otros.\n\nSirve bien al Gran Estelarca Imperial y gana un pasaje más allá del mundo limítrofe.\n\nEl nuevo sistema de misiones progresivas genera búsquedas únicas, combinando diversos objetivos, enemigos, invitados, recompensas, ayudantes, amenazas y condiciones del mundo. La expansión incorpora una gran masiva cantidad de nuevas misiones.\n\nLos mecanoides pueden ahora crear conglomerados, cada uno generado con una disposición única que presenta un desafío táctico único. Los mecaconglomerados aparecen siempre en un estado inicial durmiente, de modo que puedes preparar y ejecutar un cuidadoso ataque - o incluso usarlos contra tus enemigos.\n\nNo estás obligado a servir al Imperio. Puedes robar amplificadores psíquicos y demás tecnología Imperial. La vida del rebelde es libre, pero dura.\n\nEsta expansión incluye un nuevo álbum de música de Alistair Lindsay, compositor de la banda sonora original de RimWorld.</Royalty.description>
  
</LanguageData>