<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<LanguageData>
  
  <!-- EN: Core -->
  <Core.label>Core</Core.label>
  <!-- EN: Core RimWorld content. -->
  <Core.description>El contenido base de RimWorld.</Core.description>
  
  <!-- EN: Royalty -->
  <Royalty.label>Royalty</Royalty.label>
  <!-- EN: The Empire has arrived. Their honor-bound culture wields hyper-advanced technology, while bowing to the ancient traditions of kings, queens, titles and honor.\n\nEarn royal titles. Construct luxurious thronerooms and royal chambers. Call Imperial elite troops and bond with unique Imperial bladelink weapons.\n\nUse new psychic abilities. Blind, mind-control, nauseate, and induce insanity. Teleport, block pain, confer deadly focus, and turn invisible.\n\nServe the Imperial High Stellarch well and earn a pass off the rimworld.\n\nA new quest system procedurally generates unique quests, combining different goals, foes, guests, rewards, helpers, special threats, and world conditions. The expansion adds a large amount of new quest content.\n\nMechanoids can now create clusters of mechanoid buildings. Each mech cluster generates with a unique layout, presenting a unique tactical puzzle. Mech clusters always appear in an initially dormant state, so you can plan and execute a careful attack - or use them against your foes.\n\nYou don't have to serve the Empire. You can steal psychic amplifiers and other Imperial technology. The rebel life is free - but challenging.\n\nThis expansion includes a new album music by Alistair Lindsay, composer of the original RimWorld soundtrack. -->
  <Royalty.description>El Imperio ha llegado. Su honrada cultura posee tecnología hiper-avanzada, mientras siguen respetando sus antiguas tradiciones de reyes, reinas, títulos y honor.\n\nObtén títulos reales. Construye fastuosos salones del trono y cámaras reales. Llama a las tropas de élite Imperiales y utiliza las exclusivas armas vinculadas del Imperio.\n\nHaz uso de nuevas habilidades psíquicas. Ciega, controla mentalmente, e induce náuseas y locura. Otros poderes incluyen teletransporte, negar el dolor, o volverse invisible, entre otros.\n\nSirve bien al Gran Estelarca Imperial y gana un pasaje más allá del mundo limítrofe.\n\nEl nuevo sistema de misiones progresivas genera búsquedas únicas, combinando diversos objetivos, enemigos, invitados, recompensas, ayudantes, amenazas y condiciones del mundo. La expansión incorpora una gran masiva cantidad de nuevas misiones.\n\nLos mecanoides pueden ahora crear conglomerados, cada uno generado con una disposición única que presenta un desafío táctico único. Los meca-conglomerados aparecen siempre en un estado inicial durmiente, de modo que puedes preparar y ejecutar un cuidadoso ataque - o incluso usarlos contra tus enemigos.\n\nNo estás obligado a servir al Imperio. Puedes robar amplificadores psíquicos y demás tecnología Imperial. La vida del rebelde es libre - pero dura.\n\nEsta expansión incluye un nuevo álbum de música de Alistair Lindsay, compositor de la banda sonora original de RimWorld.</Royalty.description>
  
</LanguageData>